明斯克 白俄罗斯
Minsk Belarus.
从头开始 源源本本告诉我
Just tell me what happened from the beginning.
我们去泡吧
We had been to a bar,
酒吧不错 我开始和一个女招待搭讪
nice place, and, er, I got chatting with one of the waitresses,
凯伦她很不高兴 后来回到酒店
and Karen weren't happy with that, so…when we get back to the hotel,
我们吵起来 打了一架
we end up having a bit of a ding-dong.
她老是讽刺我 说我不似个真爷们
She's always getting at me, saying I weren't a real man.
不「是」个真爷们
Wasn't a real man.
- 什么？- 「不是」 你说的「不似」
- What? - It's not "weren't", it's "wasn't".
接着说
Go on.
然后 我也不知怎么回事
Well…then I don't know how it happened,
突然我手里就多了把刀
but suddenly there's a knife in my hands…
我老爹是个屠户 所以我会使刀
…and me old man was a butcher, so I know how to handle knives.
- 他叫我们肢解野兽 - 「教」
- He learned us how to cut up a beast. - Taught.
- 什么？- 「教」你们肢解野兽
- What? - Taught you how to cut up a beast.
嗯 反正 我就动作了
Yeah, well, then I done it.
- 「动手」 - 动手 捅了她
- Did it. - Did it! Stabbed her,
一刀一刀又一刀 等我低头看 她经已…
over and over and over, and I looked down, and she weren't…
「已经」
…wasn't…
不会东了
…moving no more.
「不会动了」
Any more.
老天 我真不知道怎么回事
God help me, I dunno how it happened,
但这是意外 我发誓
but it was an accident, I swear.
你一定得帮我 福尔摩斯先生
You've got to help me, Mr Holmes!
人人都说你是最棒的
Everyone says you're the best.
没有你…
Without you…
我会为这个被挂的
I'll get hung for this.
不不 贝维克先生 不会的
No, no, Mr Bewick, not at all.
绞死倒是会的
Hanged, yes.
《神探夏洛克》
《致命游戏》
你他妈的在干什么啊
What the hell are you doing?!
- 无聊 - 什么？
- Bored. - What?!
- 无聊 - 别…
- Bored! - No…
无聊
Bored!
无聊啊
真不知道如今的犯罪阶层都怎么了
Don't know what's got into the criminal classes.
幸好我不是其中一员
Good job I'm not one of them.
所以你拿墙出气？
So you take it out on the wall?
墙自找的
The wall had it coming.
- 俄罗斯那案子呢？- 白俄罗斯
- What about that Russian case? - Belarus?
老一套家庭情杀 浪费我时间
Open and shut domestic murder. Not worth my time.
好可惜哦
Oh, shame!
家里有吃的没？我饿死了
Anything in? I'm starving.
我草…
Oh, f…
有个人头
There's a head.
- 砍掉的人头 - 我就要茶 谢谢
- A severed head! - Just tea for me, thanks.
- 不 冰箱里有个人头 - 嗯？
- No, there's a head in the fridge. - Yes?
- 是人头喂 - 唉 我还能
- A bloody head! - Well, where else.
放在哪呢？你不介意的吧？
I supposed to put it? You don't mind, do you?
- 呃… - 从巴兹医学院太平间拿来的
- Well… - Got it from Barts morgue.
我在测量人死后唾液的凝结速度
I'm measuring the coagulation of saliva after death.
我看见你写的出租司机案了
I see you've written up the taxi driver case.
呃 对
Er…yes.
「粉色的研究」
A Study In Pink.
真好听
Nice.
你知道 粉红女郎 粉红箱子
Well, you know. Pink lady, pink case,
粉红手机 全是粉红 你喜欢吗？
pink phone. There was a lot of pink. Did you like it?
- 呃 不喜欢 - 为什么？我以为你会得意呢
- Um…no. - Why not? I thought you'd be flattered.
得意？「夏洛克能瞬间看穿一切人和事」
Flattered?! "Sherlock sees through everything and everyone in seconds.
「然而神奇的是 他同时也在某些方面」
"What's incredible, though, is how spectacularly ignorant he is.
「极其无知」
"about some things."
等等 我不是说…
Hang on, I didn't mean that…
哦 你这个「极其无知」是夸我来的
Oh, you meant "spectacularly ignorant" in a nice way!
听着 我不在乎谁是首相或者…
Look, it doesn't matter to me who's Prime Minister or…
- 我知道 - 谁和谁有奸情
- I know. - Who's sleeping with who…
地球是否绕着太阳转
Whether the Earth goes round the sun.
又是这个 这不重要
That again! It's not important!
不重要…
Not impor…?!
这是小学知识 你怎能不知道？
It's primary school stuff. How can you not know that?
就算知道过 我也删除了
Well, if I ever did, I've deleted it.
删除了？
Deleted it?
你看 这是我的硬盘 唯一合理做法是
Listen. This is my hard drive, and it only makes sense.
只存进有用的东西 真正有用的
to put things in there that are useful. REALLY useful.
普通人总在脑子里塞满垃圾
Ordinary people fill their heads with all kinds of rubbish.
有用的信息都找不到了 明白？
That makes it hard to get at the stuff that matters. Do you see?
可这是太阳系的问题啊
But it's the solar system!
拜托 有什么意义？
Oh, hell! What does that matter?!
我们绕太阳转 要是改成绕月亮转
So we go round the sun. If we went round the moon,
或者像小熊一样绕着花园转圈
or round and round the garden like a teddy bear,
不也一样吗
it wouldn't make any difference!
对我唯一重要的是工作
All that matters to me is the work!
没有工作 我脑子都要锈了
Without that, my brain rots!
写进你博客里去 或者行行好
Put that in your blog! Or, better still,
别再拿你的高见折磨全世界了
stop inflicting your opinions on the world!
- 你去哪？- 外面 我需要新鲜空气
- Where are you going? - Out! I need some air.
- 抱歉 亲爱的 - 抱歉
- Oh, sorry, love! - Sorry.
哎哟 你们俩发生家庭纠纷了？
Ooh-ooh! Have you two had a little domestic?
外面天气冷飕飕的
Ooh, it's a bit nippy out there.
他应该多穿点的
He should have wrapped himself up a bit more.
看看外面 赫德森太太
Look at that, Mrs Hudson.
寂静
Quiet.
沉静 安详
Calm. Peaceful.
何其可恶啊
Isn't it hateful?
哦 总会出点事的 夏洛克
Oh, I'm sure something will turn up, Sherlock.
出个漂亮的凶杀案 你就会开心啦
A nice murder. That'll cheer you up.
嗯 绝对是时候了
Mmm. Can't come too soon.
喂 你把我的墙壁怎么了啊
Hey, what have you done to my bloody wall?!
这个算在你房租里 小伙子
I'm putting this on your rent, young man!
- 早安 - 哦 早安
- Morning. - Oh…m-morning.
看吧 就说你该用气垫床的
See? Told you you should have gone with the Lilo.
不不 没事 我睡得挺好 谢谢你好心收留
No, no, no, it's fine, I slept fine. It's very kind of you.
也许下次我会让你睡在我被角上
Well, maybe next time I'll let you kip at the end of my bed, you know.
「被埋没在…」
…which was discovered mouldering…
- 再下次呢？- 「18个月前被发现」
- What about the time after that? - 18 months ago.
「专家将之誉为本世纪最大艺术发现」
Experts are hailing it as the artistic find of the century…
- 要早餐吗？- 好呀
- Do you want some breakfast? - Love some.
自己做吧 我去洗个澡
Well, make it yourself. I'm going to have a shower.
「最终售价高达一千万镑」
It fetched over 20 million ponds.
「这一件有望拍出更高价钱
This one is anticipated to do even better.
回到头条新闻「
Back now to our main story.
「伦敦中心区发生了一起大爆炸」
There's been a massive explosion in central London.
「目前 还没有伤亡报告
As yet, there are no reports of any casualties,
警方无法确认「
and the police are unable to say.
「这是否与恐怖分子有关」
if there's any suspicion of terrorist involvement.
- 莎拉 - 「警方公布了紧急电话」
- Sarah! - Police have issued an emergency number…
- 莎拉 - 「供当事人亲友联络」
- Sarah! - …for friends and relatives.
抱歉 我得走了
Sorry! I've got to run!
抱歉 借过一下 抱歉 借过一下
Excuse me, can I get through? Excuse me. Can I get through?
我家在里面
I live over there.
夏洛克
Sherlock!
约翰
John.
我在电视上看见了 你还好吗？
I saw it on the telly. Are you OK?
我？什么？哦 没事
Me? What? Oh, yeah, fine.
显然是煤气泄漏了
Gas leak, apparently.
- 我不能 - 不能
- I can't. - Can't?
我手头的案子太多了 抽不出空
Stuff I've got on is just too big. I can't spare the time.
别管你那些鸡毛蒜皮了 这是国家大事
Never mind your usual trivia. This is of national importance.
节食成果如何？
How's the diet?
不错
Fine.
也许你能说通他 约翰
Perhaps you can get through to him, John.
什么？
What?
恐怕我弟弟有时就是这么顽固
I'm afraid my brother can be very intransigent.
你这么热心 你自己去调查呀
If you're so keen, why don't you investigate it?
不行 我一刻也不能离开办公室
No. I can't possibly be away from the office for any length of time.
韩国大选就要…
Not with the Korean elections so…
反正你也懒得知道 对吧？
Well, you don't need to know about that, do you?
再说 这种案子需要…跑腿
Besides, a case like this, it requires…legwork.
莎拉还好吗 约翰？气垫床如何？
How's Sarah, John? How was the Lilo?
沙发 夏洛克 他睡的沙发
Sofa, Sherlock. It was the sofa.
- 哦 当然 - 怎么… 算了
- Oh, yes, of course. - How…? Oh, never mind.
夏洛克的生意日见红火了
Sherlock's business seems to be booming.
自从你和他结成…
since you and he became…
朋友 和他同居感觉如何？
pals. What's he like to live with?
- 苦不堪言吧 - 我从不无聊
- Hellish, I imagine. - I'm never bored.
好呀 那太好了 对吧
Good. That's good, isn't it?
安德鲁·韦斯特 朋友叫他小韦 公务员
Andrew West, known as Westie to his friends. Civil servant.
尸体今早在巴特西（伦敦西南）车站铁轨上出现
Found dead on the tracks at Battersea station this morning.
脑浆迸裂
with his head smashed in.
卧轨自杀？
Jumped in front of a train?
顺理成章的推断
Seems the logical assumption.
- 可是 - 可是？
- But? - But?
若是事故你也不会来了
Well, you wouldn't be here if it was just an accident.
国防部在开发新的反导弹系统
The MoD is working on a new missile defence system,
人称布鲁斯-帕廷顿计划
the Bruce-Partington Program it's called.
计划存在一根记忆棒里
The plans for it were on a memory stick.
不怎么明智啊
That wasn't very clever.
- 不是唯一一份 - 哦
- It's not the only copy. - Oh.
可也是机密
But it is secret.
而且遗失了
And missing.
顶级机密？
Top secret?
绝密 我们认为记忆棒可能被韦斯特拿了
Very. We think West must have taken the memory stick.
不能让它流入外人手里
We can't risk it falling into the wrong hands.
你得找到这份计划 夏洛克
You've got to find those plans, Sherlock.
- 别逼我命令你 - 你倒是试试呀
- Don't make me order you. - I'd like to see you try.
好好考虑
Think it over.
- 再见 约翰 - 嗯
- Goodbye, John. - Mm.
很快就会再见的
See you very soon.
你为什么撒谎？
Why did you lie?
你闲得要命
You've got nothing on.
根本没案子 墙都差点被你拆了
Not a single case. That's why the wall took a pounding.
为什么告诉你哥哥你很忙？
Why did you tell your brother you were busy?
为什么不能？
Why shouldn't I?
好呀
Nice.
兄弟斗气 这倒真有意思
Sibling rivalry. Now we're getting somewhere.
夏洛克·福尔摩斯
Sherlock Holmes.
当然 我怎么会拒绝呢？
Of course. How could I refuse?
- 是谁 - 是雷斯垂德 我被召唤了
- What's wrong? - Lestrade, I've been summoned.
来吗？
Coming?
- 只要你要我来 - 当然
- Yeah. If you want me to. - Of course.
离开我的博客作家 我就不知所措了
I'd be lost without my blogger.
你喜欢好玩的案子 对吧？
You like the funny cases, don't you?
- 有惊喜的案子 - 显然
- The surprising ones. - Obviously.
这个爆炸案包你满意
You'll love this. That explosion.
- 煤气泄漏吧？- 不
- Gas leak, yes? - No.
- 不？- 不
- No? - No.
- 故意做了那种幌子 - 什么？
- Made to look like one. - What?
整片都炸成白地了 就剩一个保险箱
Hardly anything left of the place, except a strongbox.
非常保险的保险箱 里面是这个
A VERY strong box, and inside it was this.
- 你没拆开？- 写明给你的 不是吗？
- You haven't opened it? - It's addressed to you, isn't it?
照过X光了 没有机关
We've X-rayed it. It's not booby-trapped.
真让人安心啊
How reassuring.
（夏洛克·福尔摩斯）
纸真挺括
Nice stationery.
波西米亚信笺
Bohemian.
什么？
What?
捷克出产的 没有指纹？
From the Czech Republic. No fingerprints?
没有
No.
这位女士用了自来水笔 派克世纪铱金笔
She used a fountain pen. Parker Duofold, iridium nib.
- 女士？- 显然嘛
- She? - Obviously.
显然
Obviously.
可这…是那个手机 粉红手机
But that… That's the phone. The pink phone.
「粉色的研究」里的？
What, from The Study In Pink?
显然不是同一个 但故意用同款…
Obviously, it's not the same phone, but it's supposed to look like…
「粉色的研究」？你也看他的博客？
"Study In Pink"? You read his blog?
当然 我们都爱看
Of course. We all do.
你真的不知道地球绕太阳转？
Do you REALLY not know that the Earth goes round the sun?
不是同一只手机 这个是全新的
It isn't the same phone. This one's brand-new.
有人故意选了同样的手机
Someone's taken trouble to make it look the same,
说明你的博客读者群还挺广
which means your blog has a far wider readership.
「您有一条新短信」
You have one new message.
- 就这些？- 不 不止这些
- Was that it? - No, that's not it.
这到底是跟我们搞什么鬼？
What the hell are we supposed to make of that?
一张房产广告照 该死的格林威治报时信号
An estate agent's photo and the bloody Greenwich pips.
- 是个警告 - 警告？
- It's a warning. - A warning?
有些秘密社团寄送晒干的西瓜籽
Some secret societies used to send dried melon seeds,
桔核之类的东西 信号（又意桔核）有五响
orange pips, things like that, five pips.
他们警告我们这还会再发生
They're warning us it's going to happen again.
- 我见过这个地方 - 等等
- I've seen this place before. - Hang on.
- 什么会再发生？- 轰
- What's going to happen again? - Boom!
赫德森太太
Mrs Hudson!
你看过一眼 对吧
You did a look, didn't you,
第一次来看房的时候
when you first came to see about your flat?
门最近开过
The door's been opened, recently.
不可能 只有这一把钥匙
No, can't be. That's the only key.
找不到人想租这间房
I can't get anyone interested in this flat.
太潮湿了吧 地下室就这毛病
It's the damp, I expect that's the curse of basements.
我刚结婚的时候住过 满墙的青苔
I'd a place once when I was first married. Mould all up the wall…
哦 我的天
Oh. Dear me.
鞋子
Shoes.
他是投弹手 记得吗
He's a bomber, remember.
（来电号码屏蔽）
你好
Hello.
你…好 性感帅哥
H-Hello…sexy.
哪位？
Who's this?
我给你…准备了个…小谜语
I've…sent you…a little puzzle,
这只是问个好
just to say hi.
你是谁 你哭什么？
Who's talking? Why are you crying?
我…我没有哭
I…I'm not crying.
我在打字
I'm typing.
这个…蠢婊子
And this…stupid bitch.
在替我读
is reading it out.
大幕拉开了
The curtain rises.
- 什么？- 没什么
- What? - Nothing.
你说什么？
No, what did you mean?
这一天我等了一阵子了
I've been expecting this for some time.
12小时…解开…
12 hours to solve…
我的谜语…夏洛克…
…my puzzle, Sherlock…
不然我就…
or I'm going to be…
会…捣蛋的哟…
…so…naughty.
（巴兹医学院）
- 好吧 你觉得是谁？- 嗯？
- So, who do you suppose it was? - Hmm?
电话里的 在哭的女人
Woman on the phone, the crying woman.
她不重要 她只是个人质 没线索的
Oh, she doesn't matter, she's just a hostage. No lead there.
我没说线索
I wasn't thinking about leads.
你帮不上她
You're not going to be much use to her.
他们在追踪吗 追踪手机信号
Are they trying to trace it, trace the call?
投弹手太聪明了 没用的 我的手机给我
Bomber's too smart for that. Pass my phone.
- 在哪？- 上衣兜
- Where is it? - Jacket.
当心点
Careful!
你哥哥的短信
Text from your brother.
- 删掉 - 删掉？
- Delete it. - Delete it?
计划已经流出国外了 我们没办法
Plans are out of the country. Nothing we can do.
（韦斯特之死有进展否？—麦克罗夫特）
麦克罗夫特认为我们有 他发给你八条短信了
Well, Mycroft thinks there is. He's texted you eight times.
肯定很重要
Must be important.
那他怎么还有空看牙医？
Then why didn't he cancel his dental appointment?
看什么？
His what?
他只要能说话 绝不发短信
Mycroft never texts if he can talk.
安德鲁·韦斯特偷了计划去卖
Look, Andrew West stole the missile plans, tried to sell them,
结果送掉了脑袋
got his head smashed in,
就这么回事
end of story.
唯一疑点是我哥干嘛缠着我
The only mystery is why my brother is so determined.
打扰我和这么有趣的人交锋
to bore me when somebody is being so interesting.
拜托记住有个女人快死了
Try and remember there's a woman who might die.
为什么？医院里随时都有人死去 医生
What for? There's hospitals full of people dying, Doctor.
你何不去他们床边哭哭看
Why don't you go and cry by their bedside.
能不能给他们吊命？
and see what good it does them?
（搜索完成）
- 有发现吗？- 当然
- Any luck? - Oh, yes!
抱歉 我不知道…
Oh, sorry. I didn't…
吉姆 嗨 快进来
Jim, hi! Come in! Come in!
- 吉姆 这就是夏洛克·福尔摩斯 - 啊
- Jim, this is Sherlock Holmes. - Ah.
还有…抱歉你是…
And, er… Sorry.
约翰·华生 嗨
John Watson. Hi.
嗨 你就是夏洛克·福尔摩斯啊
Hi. So you're Sherlock Holmes.
茉莉给我讲了好多你的事 你在办案吗？
Molly's told me all about you. You on one of your cases?
吉姆在楼上IT部工作
Jim works in IT, upstairs.
我们就这么认识的 办公室恋情
That's how we met. Office romance.
同性恋
Gay.
- 抱歉 什么？- 没什么 呃…嗨
- Sorry, what? - Nothing. Um, hey.
抱歉 抱歉
Sorry. Sorry!
呃 我还是走吧
Well, I'd better be off.
狐狸剧院见
I'll see you at the Fox.
- 六点钟？- 好
- About sixish? - Yeah.
- 再见 - 再见
- Bye. - Bye.
很高兴见到你
It was nice to meet you.
我们也是
You too.
你说什么同性恋？我们在交往耶
What do you mean, gay? We're together.
居家生活一定很适合你 茉莉
Domestic bliss must suit you, Molly.
几天没见你胖了三磅
You've put on 3lb since I last saw you.
- 两磅半 - 不 三磅
- Two-and-a-half. - No, three.
- 夏洛克 - 他不是同性恋
- Sherlock. - He's not gay!
你何苦非要毁掉…他不是
Why do you have to spoil…? He's not!
那么爱打扮？
With that level of grooming?
因为他头发上抹东西吗 我也抹的呀
Because he puts product in his hair? I put product in my hair.
你洗头发时抹 不一样
You wash your hair, there's a difference.
染睫毛 额头上有牛磺酸精华霜
Tinted eyelashes, signs of taurine cream around the frown lines,
泡夜店泡到满眼血丝
those tired, clubber's eyes.
- 还有他的内裤 - 他的内裤？
- Then there's his underwear. - His underwear?
腰上露出一截 非常特别的品牌
Visible above the waistline. Very particular brand.
最明显的是 他在碟子底下留了个电话
Plus the suggestive fact that he left his number under this dish.
我建议你尽早分手 免得事后伤心
I'd say you'd better break it off now and save yourself the pain.
真棒 干的漂亮
Charming, well done!
为她节省时间 不是很好心吗？
Just saving her time. Isn't that kinder?
好心？不不 夏洛克 这不是好心
Kinder? No, no, Sherlock, that wasn't kind.
说吧
Go on, then.
你知道我怎么做 试试吧
You know what I do. Off you go.
- 还是算了 - 说吧
- Oh… No. - Go on.
我不会站在这 由着你笑话我…
I'm not going to let you humiliate me while I…
旁观者清
An outside eye,
不同的意见 对我很有用
a second opinion, it's very useful to me.
- 对哦 - 真的
- Yeah, right! - Really!
好吧
Fine.
- 这只是双鞋…跑鞋 - 很好
- Oh, they're just a pair of sh…trainers. - Good.
状态很好 我觉得还挺新
They're in good nick. I'd say they were pretty new,
只有鞋底有磨损
except the sole has been well worn,
所以它的主人已经穿了一段时间了
so the owner must have had them for a while.
八十年代风格 大概是复古款
Er, very '80s. Probably one of those retro designs.
你成就惊人啊 还有呢？
You're on sparkling form. What else?
码子很大 是男人的
They're quite big. A man's.
可是…
But…
可是内侧有写名字的痕迹
But there's traces of a name inside in felt-tip.
成人不会在鞋上签名
Adults don't write their names inside their shoes,
所以是小孩的
so these belong to a kid.
太棒了 还有呢？
Excellent. What else?
- 就这些 - 就这些
- That's it. - That's it.
- 我做的怎样？- 很好 约翰
- How did I do? - Well, John.
真的很好
Really well.
我说 你几乎漏掉了所有重要信息
I mean, you missed almost everything of importance,
不过 你知道…
but, you know…
主人爱惜它 擦得很干净
The owner loved these. Scrubbed them clean.
还上了油 鞋带换了三…不 四次
Whitened them. Changed the laces three…no, four times.
手指触摸的地方
There are traces of flaky skin where his fingers.
有皮屑 所以他患了湿疹
have come into contact with them, so he had eczema.
内侧比外侧磨损严重 他足弓无力
The shoes are more worn on the inner side, so he had weak arches.
英国制造的 20年了
British-made, 20 years old.
- 20年？- 不是复古款 是原装的
- 20 years? - They're not retro, they're original.
限量版 两条蓝道 1989年的
Limited edition, two blue stripes, 1989.
上面还沾着泥 看起来很新
There's still mud on them. They look new.
有人特意保存的
Someone's kept them that way.
鞋掌沾了好几层泥
Quite a bit of mud caked on the soles.
化验出内层是苏塞克斯郡的 外层是伦敦的
Analysis shows it's from Sussex with London mud overlaying it.
- 你怎么知道？- 花粉
- How do you know? - Pollen.
清晰得像地图 泰晤士南岸
Clear as a map reference. South of the river.
这孩子20年前从苏塞克斯来伦敦
This kid came to London from Sussex 20 years ago.
- 留下了跑鞋 - 他出什么事了？
- And left the trainers behind. - What happened to him?
不是好事
Something bad.
他爱这双鞋 记得吗 绝不容许它弄脏
He loved those shoes, remember. He'd never leave them filthy.
不到万不得已 不会抛弃它
Wouldn't let them go unless he had to.
所以 一个大脚小孩来到…
So, a child with big feet gets…
什么？
What?
卡尔·鲍华
Carl Powers.
- 抱歉 谁？- 卡尔·鲍华 约翰
- Sorry, who? - Carl Powers, John.
那是什么？
What is it?
是我的起点
It's where I began.
1989年 小孩 游泳健将 从布列顿来
1989, kid, champion swimmer, came from Brighton.
参加运动会 淹死在泳池里
for a school sports tournament, drowned in the pool.
- 一场悲剧 你不会记得的 - 可你记得
- Tragic accident. You wouldn't remember it. - But you remember.
- 对 - 事有蹊跷？
- Yes. - Something fishy about it?
没人这么想
Nobody thought so.
只有我 我当时也是小孩
Nobody except me. I was only a kid myself.
在报纸上读到的
I read about it in the papers.
你起步还挺早啊
You started young, didn't you?
那男孩 卡尔·鲍华
The boy, Carl Powers,
在水中突然抽筋
had some kind of fit in the water,
可等他们救他出来 已经迟了
but by the time they got him out, it was too late.
有些事不对劲 我脑海里一直盘桓着
There was something wrong somewhere. I couldn't get it out of my head.
- 什么？- 他的鞋 - 怎么了？
- What? - His shoes. - What about them?
不见了 我大闹一场
They weren't there. I made a fuss.
我尽力想让警方注意
I tried to get the police interested,
可根本没人重视
but nobody seemed to think it was important.
其它衣服都在更衣室柜子里
He'd left all the rest of his clothes in his locker,
只有鞋不见了
but there was no sign of his shoes.
直到今天
Until now.
我能帮忙吗？
Can I help?
我想帮助你 只剩五小时了
I want to help. There's only five hours left.
（有进展吗？—麦克罗夫特）
是你哥哥
It's your brother.
现在他发给我了
He's texting me now.
他怎么有我的号？
How does he know my number?
他牙齿准是根管治疗
Must be a root canal.
- 喂 他说这是国家大事 - 哼
- Look, he did say…national importance. - Hmm!
- 真古板 - 什么？
- How quaint! - What is?
你呀 忠君爱国
You are. Queen and country.
- 你不能视而不见啊 - 我没有视而不见
- You can't just ignore it. - I'm not ignoring it.
我这就派我最出色的人去
Putting my best man onto it right now.
行啊 好
Right, good!
你指谁？
Who's that?
约翰 真荣幸 我就说马上会再见
John, how nice! I was hoping it wouldn't be long.
有什么能效劳？
How can I help you?
谢谢
Thank you.
我在等着…
Um, I was wanting to…
你弟弟派我来收集些情况
Your brother sent me to collect more facts.
关于被盗的计划 反导弹计划
about the stolen plans, the missile plans.
- 是吗？- 是的 他正在调查
- Did he? - Yes. He's investigating now.
他在… 全力调查中
He's, er…investigating away.
我想问问 关于死者你还能告诉我什么？
I just wondered what else you could tell me about the dead man.
27岁 在沃克斯豪尔当书记员
Er, 27. Clerk at Vauxhall Cross.
军情六处
MI6.
他在布鲁斯-帕廷顿计划中微不足道
He was involved in the Bruce-Partington Program in a minor capacity.
甲级保安检查 通过
Security checks A-OK.
未发现恐怖主义联系或倾向
No known terrorist affiliations or sympathies.
最后见的是他未婚妻 昨晚十点半
Last seen by his fiancee 10.30 yesterday evening.
露西亲爱的 我得出去一下
Lucy, love, I've got to go out.
我要见一个人
I've got to see someone.
小韦
Westie!
陈尸在巴特西 对 所以他乘了火车
He was found at Battersea, yes. So he got on the train?
- 没有 - 什么？
- No. - What?
他带着交通卡
He had an Oyster card…
- 但没刷过 - 他一定是买的票
- but it hadn't been used. - He must have bought a ticket.
尸体上没有车票
There was no ticket on the body.
那他怎么会脑浆迸裂
Then… How did he end up with a bashed-in brain.
死在巴特西铁轨上的？
on the tracks at Battersea?
就是这个问题
That is the question…
我希望夏洛克能解答的
the one I was rather hoping Sherlock would provide an answer to.
他进展怎样？
How's he getting on?
他挺好
He's fine.
哦 案子进展… 非常顺利
And it is going…very well.
他 呃… 全神贯注在这上面
He's, um… He's completely focused on it.
- 毒药 - 你说什么？
- Poison! - What are you going on about?
肉毒杆菌
Clostridium botulinum.
地球上最猛的毒药之一
It's one of the deadliest poisons on the planet.
卡尔·鲍华
Carl Powers.
哦，等下 你是说 他是被谋杀的？
Oh, wait. Are you saying he was murdered?
- 记得鞋带吗？- 嗯
- Remember the shoelaces? - Mmm.
他有湿疹
He suffered from eczema.
很容易把毒下到他药里
It would be easy to introduce the poison into his medication.
两小时后他来到伦敦
Two hours later he comes to London,
毒药麻痹肌肉 他淹死了
the poison paralyses the muscles and he drowns.
验尸怎么没验出来？
How come the autopsy didn't pick that up?
这无法检验 没人想到它
It's virtually undetectable. Nobody was looking for it.
（已解决 跑鞋属于卡尔·鲍华）
鞋上还有微量的残留
There are still tiny traces of it in the trainers.
（有肉毒杆菌残留 贝克街221B）
他往脚上擦药膏时留的
From where he put the cream on his feet.
因此才要藏起鞋
That's why they had to go.
我们怎么通知投弹手？
So how do we let the bomber know?
引起他注意 让计时停止
Get his attention, stop the clock.
- 凶手把鞋藏了这么多年 - 对
- The killer kept the shoes all these years. - Yes.
- 可见… - 他就是投弹手
- Meaning… - He's our bomber.
干得漂亮
"Well done, you.
来救我吧
"Come and get me."
你在哪？
Where are you?
告诉我们你在哪
Tell us where you are.
她家住康沃尔郡
She lives in Cornwall.
两个蒙面人闯入 逼她开车到停车场
Two men broke in wearing masks, forced her to drive to the car park.
停在那 身上装了能炸平一座房子的炸药
and decked her out in enough explosives to take down a house.
叫他打电话给你
Told her to phone you.
念这寻呼机上面的信息
Check the read-out from this pager.
只要念错一个字 狙击手就开枪
If she deviated by one word, the sniper would set her off.
- 或者只要你没破案 - 哦 真优雅
- Or if you hadn't solved the case. - Oh…elegant!
优雅？
Elegant?
何苦费这周折？怎么会有人想这样？
What was the point? Why would anyone do this?
哦 全世界总不止我一个人无聊吧
Oh…I can't be the only person in the world that gets bored.
「您有一条新短信」
You have one new message.
四响
Four pips.
看样子第一项考验通过了
First test passed, it would seem.
这是第二项
Here's the second.
被扔掉的报废车 不是吗？
It's abandoned, wouldn't you say?
我看看有没有记录
I'll see if it's been reported.
怪胎 找你的
Freak, it's for you.
喂
Hello.
你去找警察了 这也没关系
It's OK that you've gone to the police.
是谁？
Who is this?
又是你吗？
Is this you again?
可是别指望他们
But don't rely on them.
算你聪明
Clever you,
猜到了卡尔·鲍尔斯
guessing about Carl Powers.
我从来不喜欢他
I never liked him.
卡尔嘲笑我
Carl laughed at me,
所以我让他再也不能笑了
so I stopped him laughing.
我看 你又偷了一个人的声音吧
You've stolen another voice, I presume.
这是你和我两个人的事
This is about you and me.
你是谁？那是什么噪音？
Who are you? What's that noise?
是生命的声音啊 夏洛克
It's the sounds of life, Sherlock.
不过别担心 我马上就能解决它
But don't worry. I can soon fix that.
你九小时内解出了我上个谜语
You solved my last puzzle in nine hours.
这次给你八小时
This time you have eight.
好
Great!
查到了
We've found it.
车是昨天早上租的 顾客叫伊安·蒙克福
The car was hired yesterday morning by an Ian Monkford.
在银行工作 城市青年 现金支付
Banker of some kind. City boy. Paid in cash.
他跟妻子说去出差 但是一直没到
Told his wife he was going away on a business trip, never arrived.
- 你还在围着他转 - 呃 是啊…
- You're still hanging round him. - Yeah, well…
- 这就是两极相吸吧 - 我们不是…
- Opposites attract, I s'pose. - We're not…
你得找点兴趣爱好
You should get yourself a hobby.
集邮 火车模型什么的 安全的
Stamps, maybe. Model trains. Safer.
先告诉你声
Before you ask,
那确实是蒙克福的血 验过DNA了
yes, it's Monkford's blood.DNA checks out.
- 没尸体 - 暂时没有
- No body. - Not yet.
把血样送到实验室
Get a sample sent to the lab.
蒙克福夫人
Mrs Monkford…
是我 抱歉 有两个警官问询过我了
Yes. Sorry, but I've already spoken with two policemen.
我们不是警方 我们是…
We're not from the police, we're…
夏洛克·福尔摩斯 您先生的旧友
Sherlock HolmesVery old friend of your husband's.
我们 可以说是
We, um…
我们一起长大的
we grew up together.
抱歉 哪位？我不记得他提到过您
I'm sorry. Who? I don't think he ever mentioned you.
哦他肯定说过的 这事儿…
Oh, he must have done. This is…
简直让人伤心欲绝 难以置信
This is horrible.I mean, I just can't believe it.
我前两天才刚见过他
I only saw him the other day.
还是老样子 无忧无虑的
Same old Ian.Not a care in the world.
抱歉 我丈夫抑郁好几个月了
Sorry… My husband has been depressed for months.
你到底是谁？
Who are you?
租车的行为很奇怪 他为什么要这么做呢
Really strange that he hired a car.Why would he do that?
有点可疑啊 您不觉得么
It's a bit suspicious, isn't it?
我没觉得 他忘了续交私车的税而已
No, it isn't. He forgot to renew the tax on the car, that's all.
原来如此 果然是伊安
Ah, well! That was Ian.
- 伊安以前总这副德行 - 伊安从没这样
- That was Ian all over. - No, it wasn't.
以前不是么 有意思
Wasn't it? Interesting.
- 那人是谁？- 你为什么要骗她？
- Who was that? - Why did you lie to her?
人不爱主动说出真相
People don't like telling you things.
但他们总喜欢反驳 过去时 注意到了么
but they love to contradict you.Past tense, did you notice?
- 什么？- 我以谈论死人的方式 用的过去时
- What? - I referred to her husband in the past tense.
她也用了
She joined in.
真武断
Bit premature.
警方才刚刚发现车子
They've only just found the car.
你认为她谋杀亲夫？
You think she murdered her husband?
- 谋杀犯不会蠢到犯这种错 - 懂了
- That's not a mistake a murderer would make. - I see…
- 不 还是不懂 应该怎样？- 钓鱼
- No, I don't. What am I seeing? - Fishing.
- 试试钓鱼 - 现在去哪儿？
- Try fishing. - Where now?
杰纳斯租车行
Janus Cars.
在仪表板下的储物箱里发现的
Just found this in the glove compartment.
恐怕我帮不上忙啦
Can't see how I can help you gentlemen.
蒙克福先生昨天
Mr Monkford hired the car.
- 在贵公司租了辆车 - 是 很赞的型号
- from you yesterday. - Yeah, lovely motor.
马自达 RX8 我本人也很喜欢
Mazda RX8.Wouldn't mind one of them myself.
就是那种？
Is that one?
不 那些都是捷豹
No, they're all Jags.
看来你并不是爱车一族？
I can see you're not a car man, eh?
但你肯定买得起一辆马自达
But surely you can afford one, a Mazda, I mean.
没错
Yeah, fair point.
就像在糖果店工作
It's like working in a sweet shop.
尝过甘草什锦糖 就会一发不可收拾？
Once you start eating the Liquorice Allsorts, where does it stop?
你不认识蒙克福先生？
You didn't know Mr Monkford.
不 只是客户而已
No, he was just a client.
他昨天来的 从我这儿租走辆车
He came in here and hired one of my cars.
对他的事我毫不知情 可怜
I've no idea what happened to him.Poor sod!
- 假期可好 伊华德先生？- 什么？
- Nice holiday, Mr Ewart? - Eh?
- 近期出国过吧？- 哦 是…
- You've been away, haven't you? - Oh, the…
不 是日光浴床晒的
No, it's sun beds, I'm afraid.
工作太忙了走不开
Too busy to get away.
不过我老婆会喜欢 海滨晒太阳
My wife would love it, though bit of sun.
有零钱么 自动售货机买烟的
Have you got any change for the cigarette machine?
什么？
What?
进来时看到有 烟瘾上来了
I noticed one on the way in and I'm gasping.
没有 不好意思
No, sorry.
好吧 谢谢 伊华德先生 打扰了
Oh, well! Thank you very much for your time, Mr Ewart.
您可帮了我们大忙 约翰 走吧
You've been very helpful. Come on, John!
我有零钱 如果你想…
I've got change, if you still want to…
尼古丁贴片 记得吧 我戒烟顺利
Nicotine patches, remember? I'm doing well.
那你刚才是要干嘛
So, what was all that about?
我要看看他的钱包
I needed to look inside his wallet.
- 干嘛 - 伊华德先生是个骗子
- Why? - Mr Ewart's a liar.
（来电号码屏蔽）
喂
Hello.
线索在名字中 杰纳斯租车行
The clue's in the name, Janus Cars.
你为什么突然好心来提示我？
Why would you be giving me a clue?
万事皆有理由
Why does anyone do anything?
因为我无聊嘛
Because I'm bored.
我们注定互相牵绊 夏洛克
We were made for each other, Sherlock.
- 那你自己打电话给我 - 耐心点
- Then talk to me in your own voice. - Patience.
你说驾驶座上的血有多少？
How much blood was on that seat, would you say?
多少？大约一品脱
How much? About a pint.
不是大约 正好一品脱 他们犯的第一个错误
Not about. Exactly a pint.That was their first mistake.
这血确实属于伊安 但是冷冻血
The blood's Ian Monkford's, but it's been frozen.
- 冷冻血？- 有明显的迹象
- Frozen? - There are clear signs.
我认为伊安·蒙克福之前抽了一品脱血
I think Ian Monkford gav a pint of his blood some time ago.
- 然后他们洒在这里 - 谁干的？
- And that's what they spread on the seat. - Who did?
杰纳斯租车行 线索就在名字里
Janus Cars. The clue's in the name.
- 罗马神话的两面天门神？- 没错
- The god with two faces? - Exactly.
他们提供特殊服务
They provide a very special service.
要是委托人有任何麻烦 债务
If you've got any kind of a problem, money troubles,
婚变 无论什么 杰纳斯帮你消失
bad marriage, whatever, Janus Cars will help you disappear.
蒙克福有麻烦 估计是财务问题
Ian Monkford was in trouble, financial at a guess,
他在银行工作嘛 他走投无路
he's a banker, couldn't see a way out.
但如果他人间蒸发
But if he were to vanish,
只要他租的车沾满他的血被发现…
if the car he hired was found with his blood on the driver's seat…
- 那他人到底在哪 - 哥伦比亚
- So where is he? - Colombia.
哥伦比亚？
Colombia?!
杰纳斯车行的伊华德先生
Mr Ewart, of Janus Cars,
钱包里有一张两万哥伦比亚比索
had a 20, 000 Colombian peso note in his wallet.
以及不少比索零钱
Quite a bit of change, too.
但他说最近没有出国过
He told us he hadn't been abroad recently,
但当我问他车型时
but when I asked him about the cars,
他颈上晒痕清晰可见
I could see his tan line clearly.
没人穿衬衫去照日光浴
No-one wears a shirt on a sun bed.
- 还有他的手臂 - 他的手臂？
- That, plus his arm. - His arm?
他不断在挠 显然很痒 而且在渗血
He kept scratching it. Obviously irritating him, and bleeding.
刚打过疫苗 可能是乙肝疫苗
He'd recently had a booster jab.Hep-B, probably.
距离太远 不确定
Hard to tell at that distance.
结论 他安排好伊安·蒙克福
He's just back from settling Ian Monkfod.
在哥伦比亚的新生活刚回来
into his new life in Colombia.
蒙克福夫人领保险金
Mrs Monkford cashes in the life insurance,
和杰纳斯车行分赃
and she splits it with Janus Cars.
- 蒙克福夫人？- 是的 她也是共犯
- Mrs Monkford? - Oh, yes. She's in on it too.
去逮捕吧 探长 你最擅长这了
Go and arrest them, Inspector, that's what you do best.
得让投弹人知道案子解决了
We need to let our bomber know the case is solved.
我真是斗志昂扬
I am on fire!
（伊安·蒙克福搬去哥伦比亚了 贺乔迁之喜）
他说…
He says…
你们可以来救我了
you can come and fetch me.
救命
Help!
救救我 求你们救我
Help me, please!
- 好点了么 - 嗯
- Feeling better? - Mmm.
这事开始后 喘气的机会都没有
We've hardly stopped for breath since this thing started.
- 你想过没… - 大概吧
- Has it occurred to you…? - Probably.
不 我是说你想过
No, has it occurred to you that.
这投弹人是在跟你玩智力游戏
the bomber's playing a game with you?
信封 闯进别人家
The envelope, breaking into the other flat,
- 去世小孩的鞋 都是给你出的题 - 我知道
- the dead kid's shoes, it's all meant for you. - Yes, I know.
那是他么 莫里亚蒂
Is it him, then? Moriarty?
有可能
Perhaps.
- 这可能是随便什么人 - 可能 嗯
- That could be anybody. - It could be, yeah.
算你走运 有我待业在家闲得发霉
Lucky for you, I've been more than a little unemployed.
什么意思？
How d'you mean?
我和赫德森太太看太多电视了
Lucky for you, Mrs Hudson and I watch far too much telly.
谢谢你 泰拉 大家看
…Thank you, Tyra!
她现在是不是靓丽可人了呢
Doesn't she look lovely, everybody, now?
无论如何 说到丝质手袋…
Anyway…speaking of silk purses…
喂
Hello?
这次的目标…
This one…
有点儿…
is a bit…
残障
…defective.
不好意思
Sorry.
她是个瞎子
She's blind.
这次的案子
This is…
很有趣
…a funny one.
我给你
I'll give you…
十二小时
…12 hours.
你为什么要这么做
Why are you doing this?
我喜欢
I like…
在暗处看你
…to watch you…
翩翩起舞
dance.
我发现你又重拾恶习了
…And I see you're back to your bad habits.
继续报道
…Continuing into.
电视界名人康妮·普林斯猝死
the sudden death of the popular TV personality Connie Prince.
「美丽俏佳人」主持普林斯女士
Miss Prince, famous for her makeover programmes,
两天前被发现在
was found dead two days ago.
与其弟合住的房子里死亡
by her brother in the house they shared…
康妮·普林斯 54岁
Connie Prince, 54.
是电视上一个美容节目的主持人
She had one of those makeover shows on the telly.
- 你看过么 - 没有
- Did you see it? - No.
- 非常红 前景光明 - 都灰飞烟灭了
- Very popular. She was going places. - Not any more.
死去两天了
Dead two days.
她的员工劳尔·德·桑托斯说
According to one of her staff, Raoul de Santos,
她被园子里一根锈钉子扎伤了手 伤得不轻
she cut her hand on a rusty nail in the garden. Nasty wound.
破伤风病菌进入血液循环 双眼一闭两腿一蹬
Tetanus bacteria enters the bloodstream, good night, Vienna.
差不多吧
I s'pose.
- 但这有点说不通 - 哈？
- Something's wrong with this picture. - Eh?
不可能这么简单
Can't be that simple,
否则投弹人不会让我们来查这个的
otherwise the bomber wouldn't be directing us towards it.
肯定有不对的地方
Something's wrong.
- 约翰 - 在
- John? - Mm.
她手上的伤口非常深
Cut on her hand, it's deep.
应该会大量出血 是吧
Would have bled a lot, right?
- 对 - 但伤口周围很干净
- Yeah. - But the wound's clean.
很干净 也很新
Very clean, and fresh.
病菌在她体内繁殖了多久？
How long would the bacteria have been incubating inside her?
八到十天吧
Oh, eight, ten days.
伤口是事后出现的
The cut was made later.
- 在她死后？- 基本可以肯定
- After she was dead? - Must have been.
唯一的问题是
The only question is,
病毒怎么进入死人体内的
how did the tetanus enter the dead woman's system?
- 你说过想帮我吧 - 当然
- You want to help, right? - Of course.
康妮·普林斯的背景 家族史
Connie Prince's background, family history,
- 一切的一切 都收集来 - 好
- everything, get me data. - Right.
- 还有件事没考虑到 - 有么
- There's something else that we haven't thought of. - Is there?
没错 投弹人为什么要这么做
Yes. Why is he doing this the bomber?
就算她死得可疑 为什么要提醒我们？
If this woman's death was suspicious, why point it up?
人性本善呗
Good Samaritan.
那还逼人自爆？
Who press-gangs suicide bombers?
人性本恶呗
Bad Samaritan.
没跟你开玩笑 夏洛克
I'm…I'm serious, Sherlock.
听着 我由着你随心去调查 我信任你
Listen, I'm cutting you slack here, I'm trusting you,
但某处有个可怜人正浑身裹着炸弹
but out there somewhere, some poor bastard's covered in Semtex.
等你解开谜题救他一命
and he's just waiting for you to solve the puzzle,
所以 请告诉我 我们到底在对付什么？
so just tell me, what are we dealing with?
前无古人的东西
Something new.
关联 关联 关联 肯定有关联存在
Connection, connection, connection. There must be a connection.
卡尔·鲍华 二十年前被害
Carl Powers, killed 20 years ago.
投弹人承认认识这人
The bomber knew him, admitted that he knew him.
他的手机装在捷克产的信封里
The bomber's iPhone was in the stationery from the Czech Republic.
第一个人质来自康沃尔 第二个伦敦
The first hostage from Cornwall, the second from London,
第三个听口音是约克夏
the third from Yorkshire, judging by her accent.
他在干什么 炫耀他的足迹遍布世界各地？
What's he doing? Working his way round the world, showing off?
看来你很享受这一切嘛
You're enjoying this, aren't you?
连点成线
Joining the…dots.
还有三个小时
Three hours.
不然就炸上天咯
Boom…boom.
伤心欲绝 真的是伤心欲绝
We're devastated, of course we are.
喝点什么 先生？
Can I get you anything, sir?
不了 谢谢
Er, no. No, thanks.
劳尔是我的救星 没了他我真不知该怎么办
Raoul is my rock. I don't think I could have managed.
我们有过些小摩擦 但姐姐跟我还是很亲的
We didn't always see eye to eye…but my sister was very dear to me.
那对于公众呢 普林斯先生
And to the, er, public, Mr Prince.
她相当受欢迎
Oh, she was adored.
我亲眼见过长得像公交车屁股的姑娘
I've seen her take girls who looked like the back end of Routemasters.
经过她的打造变成公主
and turn them into princesses.
不过 我很欣慰
Still, it's a relief, in a way,
知道她脱离了红尘苦海 往生极乐
to know that she's beyond this vale of tears.
当然了
Absolutely.
太好了
Great.
谢谢 多谢
Thank you. Thanks again.
真可惜 我真的很喜欢她
It's a real shame. I liked her.
她教人怎么配色
She taught you how to do your colours.
- 配色？- 色彩搭配一类的
- Colours? - You know, what goes best with what.
显然我不适合穿樱桃红的衣服
I should never wear cerise, apparently.
- 衬得我很苍白 - 那是谁的电话？
- Drains me. - Who's that?
- 内政部 - 内政部？
- Home Office. - Home Office?
- 其实是内政部长 欠我个人情 - 是个美女
- Well, Home Secretary, actually. Owes me a favour. - A pretty girl,
但她喜欢折腾自己的身体
but she messed about with herself too much.
明星都打肉毒杆菌 他们脸都僵住了
They all do these days.People can hardly move their faces.
太愚蠢了 不是么？
It's silly, isn't it?
- 你看过她的节目么？- 这就看
- Did you ever see her show? - Not until now.
亲爱的 你看起来好苍白
You look pasty, love.
老下雨 只有一天不下的
Ah, rained every day but one…
她弟弟 毫不伤心
That's the brother.No love lost there,
- 八卦报纸上说的 - 我也听说了
- if you can believe the papers. - So I gather.
刚才跟节目粉丝们聊了聊 收获颇丰
I've just had a fruitful chat with people who love this show.
粉丝站是八卦的不二来源
The fan site's indispensable for gossip.
你们同意吧 姑娘们
…Don't you think, girls?
下去 下去 下去 下去
Off, off, off, off, off, off, off!
人们想不到有这么多时候
It's more common than people think.
破伤风藏在土壤里
The tetanus is in the soil,
被玫瑰花刺 园丁剪割伤
people cut themselves on rose bushes, garden forks,
诸如此类 如果延误了治疗…
that sort of thing, and if left un…treated…
- 我不知道该怎么办了 - 哦
- I don't know what I'm going to do now. - Right.
她把这房子留给了我 这很好
I mean, she's left me this place…which is lovely…
但没有她就不一样了
…but it's not the same without her.
这就是为什么
That's why…
我们报纸想听你
my paper wanted to get the,
亲口说说这整个故事
um…the full story straight from the horse's mouth.
真不会太冒失吗？
Are you sure it's not too soon?
- 不会 - 好的
- No. - Right.
你尽管问
You fire away.
- 约翰 - 喂 快过来 我有新发现
- John. - Hi. Look, get over here quickly. I think I'm onto something.
路上要买点儿东西 手边有笔么
You'll need to pick up some stuff first. Got a pen?
我记得住
I'll remember.
- 就是他了 - 是么？
- That'll be him. - What?
- 您是普林斯先生吧 - 是我
- Ah, Mr Prince, isn't it? - Yes.
- 很高兴见到你 - 我也是
- Very good to meet you. - Yes, thank you.
- 请节哀顺变 - 多谢您关心
- So sorry to hear about… - Yes, yes, very kind.
过来一下
Shall we, er…?
你说得对 病菌从别的途径进入她体内
You were right, the bacteria got into her another way.
- 是么？- 没错
- Oh, yes? - Yes.
准备好了？
Right, are we all set?
好了 来吧
Er, yes. Shall we, um…?
别拍太近 拍哭我不在行
Not too close. I'm raw from crying.
咦 这是谁？
Oh, who's this?
塞克荷迈特 以埃及女神命名
Sekhmet. Named after the Egyptian goddess.
真典雅 康妮养的？
How nice. Was she Connie's?
对 鄙人送她的礼物
Yes, a little present from yours truly.
夏洛克 检测下色度吧
Sherlock, light reading?
- 2.8 该死 搞什么鬼？- 对不起
- 2.8. Bloody hell!What are you playing at? - Sorry!
你们俩怎么像说相声一样 怎么回事
You're like Laurel and bloody Hardy, you two! What's going on?
我们已经完工了 失陪
I think we've got what we came for.Excuse us.
什么 夏洛克 干嘛？
What?Sherlock. What?
走了 赶发稿了
We've got deadlines.
但你们什么都没拍哪
But you've not taken anything!
哦 太赞了
Yes! Ooh, yes!
你认为是猫？才不是呢
You think it was the cat.It wasn't the cat.
什么？就是 肯定是
What? Yes. Yeah, it is.
她一定是这样染上病毒的
It must be. It's how he got the tetanus into her system.
- 它爪子上有消毒水味 - 想法很可爱
- Its paws stink of disinfectant. - Lovely idea.
不 他涂到猫脚趾上的
No, he coated it onto the claws of her cat.
猫刚来没几天 肯定跟她不亲
It's a new pet, bound to be a bit jumpy around her.
抓伤根本难以避免
A scratch is almost inevitable.
看到她手臂上的伤我就想到了
I thought of it when I saw the scratches on her arm,
但这几率太低
but it's too random.
她弟弟也想不出来
and clever for the brother.
- 他为了遗产谋杀了她 - 是么？
- He murdered his sister for her money. - Did he?
不是么？
Didn't he?
不 这是复仇
Nope. It was revenge.
- 复仇 谁要复仇？- 劳尔 那个男仆
- Rev…? Who wanted revenge? - Raoul, the houseboy.
肯尼是他姐姐调笑的对象
Kenny Prince was the bu of his sister's jokes.
简直是家暴 最后他忍无可忍了
Virtual bullying campaign. Finally, he had enough,
跟她决裂了 网上到处写着
fell out with her badly. It's all on the website.
她威胁要取消他的继承权
She threatened to disinherit Kenny,
- 但劳尔已经习惯了这种生活 - 等等
- Raoul had grown accustomed to a certain lifestyle… - Wait. Wait!
等一下 猫爪子上的消毒水怎么解释呢
Wait a second. What about the disinfectant on the cat's claws?
劳尔有洁癖 你从厨房门进去的
Raoul keeps a very clean house.You came through the kitchen door,
你也看见地板了 光可鉴人
saw the state of that floor scrubbed within an inch of its life.
有消毒水味的是你自己 猫是无辜的
You smell of disinfectant. No, the cat doesn't come into it.
不过劳尔的网络记录就不是了
Raoul's internet records do, though.
希望在这能叫到车
I hope we can get a cab from here.
凶手是劳尔·德·桑托斯
Raoul de Santos is your killer.
肯尼·普林斯的男仆
Kenny Prince's houseboy.
第二次尸检发现
Second autopsy shows.
康妮·普林斯并非死于破伤风
it wasn't tetanus that poisoned Connie Prince,
而是A型肉毒素
it was botulinum toxin.
又是这样 卡尔·鲍华 啧啧
We've been here beforeCarl Powers. Tut-tut.
投弹人在重蹈覆辙了
Our bomber's repeated himself.
怎么做到的？
So how'd he do it?
- 注射肉毒杆菌 - 肉毒杆菌？
- Botox injection. - Botox?
肉毒杆菌是稀释的肉毒毒 除了家务
Botox is a diluted form of botulinum. Among other things,
劳尔·德·桑托斯的工作还有
Raoul de Santos was employed to.
给康妮做面部注射
give Connie her regular facial injections.
我内政部的内线给了我
My contact at the Home Office gave me.
劳尔的网购记录
the complete records of Raoul's internet purchases.
他大量订购肉毒杆菌好几个月了
He's been bulk-ordering Botox for months.
积累了一段时间 足够致死
Bided his time, then upped the strength to a fatal dose.
- 你确定？- 我确定
- Are you sure about this? - I'm sure.
好 到我办公室来
All right, my office.
- 夏洛克 多久了？- 什么
- Hey, Sherlock, how long? - What?
你想到多久了？
How long have you known?
这次其实很简单
Well, this one was quite simple.
投弹人重蹈覆辙了 一个错误
And the bomber repeated himself.That was a mistake.
但是夏洛克 人质 那位老妇人
No, but Sherlock, the hostage, the old woman,
她还绑着炸弹呢
she's been there all this time!
我确定我能救她
I knew I could save her.
我也知道我们有十二小时
I also knew that the bomber had given us 12 hours.
如果我尽快解决
I solved the case quickly,
我就有时间去查别的
that gave me time to get on with other things.
还不懂？这次我们领先了
Don't you see? We're one up on him.
（劳尔·德·桑切斯 男仆 肉毒杆菌）
喂
Hello?
救我
Help me!
告诉我你在哪儿
Tell us where you are.
- 地址 - 他非常的…
- Address? - He was so…
他的声音
His voice…
不不 不要跟我说他
No, no, no, no!Tell me nothing about him, nothing.
他的声音非常温柔
He sounded so soft.
喂
Hello?
夏洛克
Sherlock?
发生什么了？
What's happened?
此次爆炸
The explosion,
震穿了多层楼面 共十二人身亡
which ripped through several floors, killing 12 people…
- 老公寓楼 - 原因是煤气泄漏
- Old block of flats. - …caused by a faulty gas main.
燃气公司发言人表示…
A spokesman from the utility company…
他真神通广大
He certainly gets about.
显然我输了这一轮
Well, obviously I lost that round.
虽然其实我解决了这个案子
Although technically, I did solve the case.
老妇人因为透露了他的信息被杀害
He killed the old lady because she started to describe him.
仅此一次 他自己上了前线
Just once, he put himself in the firing line.
什么意思？
What d'you mean?
通常 他从高处统筹一切
Well, usually, he…must stay above it all.
他组织策划 但一般不跟人直接接触
He organises these things, but no-one ever has direct contact.
是说康妮·普林斯的谋杀是他策划的？
What, like the Connie Prince murder he arranged that?
难道人们找他策划谋杀
So, people come to him wanting their crimes fixed up,
像策划度假那样？
like booking a holiday?
有创意
Novel.
他这回慢慢来了
Taking his time this time.
卡尔·鲍华案有进展么
Anything on the Carl Powers case?
没有
Nothing.
所有在世的同学都查了 没有线索
All the living classmates check out spotless, no connection.
- 也许凶手比卡尔年长？- 我也想过
- Maybe the killer was older than Carl? - The thought had occurred.
那他为什么呢？
So why is he doing this, then?
跟你玩这个智力游戏 难道他想被抓住？
Playing this game with you.Do you think he wants to be caught?
大概他是想打发无聊
I think he wants to be distracted.
祝你们俩终成眷属吧
I hope you'll be very happy together.
- 你说什么？- 人命关天 夏洛克
- Sorry, what? - There are lives at stake, Sherlock.
活生生的生命 我想知道
Actual human lives! Just so I know,
你是不是完全不在意？
do you care about that at all?
- 在意就能救人命了？- 不能
- Will caring about them help save them? - Nope.
那我会继续避免这种错误
Then I'll continue not to make that mistake.
- 你觉得很容易吧？- 对 简单得很
- And you find that easy, do you? - Yes, very.
- 你很吃惊吗？- 不 当然不了
- Is that news to you? - No, no.
我让你失望了
I've disappointed you.
不错 演绎分析得对
That's good, that's a good deduction, yeah.
别把人当成英雄 约翰
Don't make people into heroes, John.
英雄并不存在 就算真存在
Heroes don't exist, and if they did,
我也不在其列
I wouldn't be one of them.
太好了
Excellent.
泰晤士河景观
A view of the Thames.
南岸 索斯沃克桥和滑铁卢桥间的某处
South Bank, somewhere between Southwark Bridge and Waterloo.
你查报纸 我上网看看
You check the papers, I'll look online.
你生我气了 不愿意帮忙了
Oh, you're angry with me, so you won't help.
看来「在意」也不过如此嘛
Not much cop, this caring lark.
（搜索 泰晤士： 涨潮 河岸）
（涨潮期 泰晤士河水质 伦敦大桥）
（本地新闻 格林威治 滑铁卢 巴特西）
（滑铁卢 02：16涨潮）
（04：00警方报告）
- 跳桥自杀 - 不值一提
- Archway suicide… - Ten-a-penny.
（本地新闻 格林威治 滑铁卢 巴特西）
（巴特西 无新讯息）
两儿童在斯托克纽因顿被刺伤
Two kids stabbed in Stoke Newington.
（泰晤士警方报告 值班记录）
（08：00无报告）
火车轨道上发现男尸 名为安德鲁·韦斯特
Ah, man found on the train lineAndrew West.
一无所获
Nothing!
是我 有没有
It's me. Have you found anything.
南岸滑铁卢桥和索斯沃克桥间的新案子？
on the South Bank between Waterloo Bridge and Southwark Bridge?
你认为这跟投弹人有关？
Do you reckon this is connected, then, the bomber?
肯定有 虽然很奇怪他还没联络
Must be. Odd, though, he hasn't been in touch.
又得假定有倒霉蛋被绑上炸弹啰？
Then we must assume that some poor bugger's primed to explode, yeah?
是的
Yes.
- 有想法么？- 目前为止 有七个
- Any ideas? - Seven, so far.
七个？
Seven?
距离他死亡已有二十四小时
He's dead about 24 hours.
- 可能再长一些 - 淹死的？
- Maybe a bit longer. - Did he drown?
（国际刑警 通缉犯 犯罪团伙 地方违规）
明显不是 肺里没什么河水 窒息而死
Apparently not. Not enough of the Thames in his lungs. Asphyxiated.
我同意
Yes, I'd agree.
（捷克共和国）
口鼻周围有不少淤痕
There's quite a bit of bruising around the nose and mouth.
（捷克共和国 团伙 通缉）
还有些淤痕
More bruises…
分别在这里和这里
here and here.
指印
Fingertips.
（失踪人口 36小时内 本地）
他年近四十 处于亚健康状态
He's late 30s, I'd say, not in the best condition.
尸体在河里很久了
He's been in the river a long while,
水泡掉了大部分信息
the water's destroyed most of the data.
但我告诉你们一件事
But I'll tell you one thing,
新发现的维米尔油画是赝品
that lost Vermeer painting's a fake.
- 什么？- 得查出被害人身份
- What? - We need to identify the corpse,
找到他的朋友和…
find out about his friends and…
等等 什么油画 你在说什么？
Wait, wait, wait, wait. What painting? What are you on about?
都传遍了 你没看到海报？
It's all over the place, haven't you seen the posters?
荷兰大师遗作 本以为几世纪前被毁的
Dutch old master, supposed to have been destroyed centuries ago.
最近被发现了 价值三千万英镑
Now it's turned up, worth 30 million.
好吧 那跟案子有何关系？
OK, so what has that got to do with the stiff?
休戚相关哪
Everything.
- 你听说过泥人哥连么 - 泥人哥连？
- Have you ever heard of the Golem? - Golem?
恐怖电影？说这干什么？
It's a horror story, isn't it?What are you saying?
犹太民间故事 泥土制成的巨人
Jewish folk story, a gigantic man made of clay.
也是个杀手的代号
it's also the name of an assassin.
真名奥斯卡·杜斯拉
Real name, Oskar Dzundza.
世界顶级杀手之一
One of the deadliest assassins in the world.
这是他的标志性手段
That is his trademark style.
- 买凶杀人？- 肯定
- So this is a hit? - Definitely.
泥人空手把他的目标勒死
The Golem squeezes the life out of his victims with his bare hands.
这又跟油画有什么关系 我没看出…
But what has this got to do with that painting? I don't see…
你看到了 只是不会观察
You do see, you just don't observe!
行了别吵了 小姐们 都冷静点
Yes, all right, all right, girls!Calm down.
夏洛克 能否劳驾解释一下？
Sherlock, do you want to take us through it?
关于这具尸体我们都知道点什么
What do we know about this corpse?
凶手没留下多少线索 只有裤子和衬衫
The killer's not left us with much, just the shirt and the trousers.
很正式 可能他晚上有约会
They're pretty formal, maybe he was going out for the night.
裤子很结实 涤纶的便宜货 衬衫也一样
The trousers are heavy duty.Polyester, nasty, same as the shirt, cheap.
对他都太大了 应该是统一制服
They're both too big for him. So some kind of standard-issue uniform.
是去上班 哪种工作呢？
Dressed for work, then.What kind of work?
皮带上有个装对讲机的搭扣
There's a hook on his belt…for a walkie-talkie.
地铁司机？
Tube driver?
- 保安？- 更有可能
- Security guard? - More likely.
- 由他的臀部证实了 - 臀部？
- That'll be borne out by his backside. - Backside?!
臀部松弛 说明他总坐着
Flabby, you'd think he'd led a sedentary life.
但他脚掌和腿上的静脉曲张
Yet the soles of his feet and the nascent varicose veins in his legs.
又表明了不同情况
show otherwise.
经常走动也经常坐着
So, a lot of walking and a lot of sitting around.
看来确实是保安 手表也有帮助
Security guard's looking good.The watch helps too.
闹钟显示他常值夜班
The alarm shows he did regular night shifts.
也许他前一天晚上刚设了闹钟呢
Maybe he just set his alarm like that the night before he died.
不不 按钮很硬 说明不常碰
No, no, no. The buttons are stiff, hardly touched.
很久以前设的 生活一成不变
He set his alarm like that a long time ago, his routine never varied.
还有别的 杀手可能被打断了
But there's something else. The killer must have been interrupted,
否则他肯定把衣服扒光
otherwise he would have stripped the corpse completely.
衬衫前胸本来有徽章或标志
There was some kind of badge or insignia on the shirt front.
凶手撕了 说明死者在大公司
that he tore off, suggesting the dead man.
某种公共机构工作
some kind of institution.
我在他裤子口袋里发现了这个
I found this inside his trouser pockets.
被河水泡了 但还看得出来
Sodden by the river, but still recognisably…
- 票？- 票根
- Tickets? - Ticket stubs.
在博物馆或画廊工作 经我搜索
He worked in a museum or gallery.Did a quick check.
希克曼画廊报警说
The Hickman Gallery has reported.
有一名员工失踪 亚历克斯·伍德布基
one of its attendants as missing, Alex Woodbridge.
今晚 他们要展出新发现的油画
Tonight, they unveil the rediscovered masterpiece.
为什么有人要雇佣泥人
Now, why would anyone want to pay the Golem.
去掐死一个画廊的小小员工呢
to suffocate a perfectly ordinary gallery attendant?
结论 死者知道内情
Inference, the dead man knew something about it,
会让画主人赚不到三千万的内情
something that would stop the owner getting paid 30 million.
- 那幅画是赝品 - 太神奇了
- The pictures are fake. - Fantastic.
- 圣诞小把戏 - 顺祝新年好
- Meretricious. - And a Happy New Year.
可怜的家伙
Poor sod.
我最好派探子去打听一下这个泥人
I'd better get my feelers out for this Golem character.
没用 你找不到他 但我知道谁能
Pointless, you'll never find him, but I know a man who can.
- 谁？- 我
- Who? - Me.
他为什么不来电话？
Why hasn't he phoned?
他破坏自己的规律 为什么？
He's broken his pattern. Why?
- 滑铁卢桥 - 现在去哪儿 画廊？
- Waterloo Bridge. - Where now, the gallery?
等一下去
In a bit.
希克曼现代画廊 是吧
The Hickman's contemporary art, isn't it?
- 他们怎么会找到古画呢 - 不清楚
- Why have they got hold of an old master? - Don't know.
妄下结论是很危险的
Dangerous to jump to conclusions.
需要资讯
Need data…
停车
Stop!
稍等会好么
Can you wait here?
我去去就回
I won't be a moment.
夏洛克
Sherlock?
零钱 有零钱吗？
Change? Any change?
- 要干嘛 - 当然是拿去喝茶
- What for? - Cup of tea, of course.
给你 50镑
Here you go, 50.
多谢
Thanks.
- 你这是干什么？- 投资
- What are you doing? - Investing.
现在去画廊 你有现金么？
Now we go to the gallery.Have you got any cash?
你不用来 去查那保安的一切资料
No, I need you to find out all you can about the gallery attendant.
- 雷斯垂德会给你地址的 - 好
- Lestrade will give you the address. - OK.
我们合住了一年了
We'd been sharing about a year.
室友而已
Just sharing.
- 我能看看么？- 当然
- May I? - Yeah.
抱歉
Sorry.
他喜欢天文啊
Stargazer, was he?
是啊 爱得如痴如狂
God, yeah. Mad about it.
这是他唯一的业余爱好
It's all he ever did in his spare time.
阿历克斯人很好
He was a nice guy, Alex.
我很喜欢他
I liked him.
他呢
He was, er…
他不爱打扫
never much of a one for hoovering.
艺术呢 他喜欢艺术么？
What about art?Did he know anything about that?
那只是工作 糊口罢了
It was just a job, you know?
最近有人来打听阿历克斯吗？
Has anyone else been round asking about Alex?
没有
No.
倒是有人非法闯入
We had a break-in, though.
- 什么时候 - 昨晚
- When? - Last night.
什么都没丢
There was nothing taken.
还有一条给阿历克斯的电话留言
Oh, there was a message left for Alex on the land line.
- 谁留的？- 你想听我可以放给你听
- Who was it from? - I can play it for you, if you like.
- 我去拿电话 - 麻烦了
- I'll get the phone. - Please.
开始录音了？阿历克斯
Oh, should I speak now? Alex?
亲爱的 我是凯安斯教授
Love, it's Professor Cairns.
听着 你是对的 完全正确
Listen, you were right.You were bloody right.
有空给我们回个电…
Give us a call when…
凯安斯教授？
Professor Cairns?
- 不知道 抱歉 - 没事
- No idea, sorry. - Mmm.
我能回拨么？
Can I try and ring back?
不行了 我接过好几个慰问电话了
No good. I've had other calls since.Sympathy ones, you know.
（回复：布鲁斯-帕廷顿计划）
（和韦斯特未婚妻谈了吗 —麦克罗夫特）
（希克曼画廊）
你没有活要干了？
Don't you have something to do?
欣赏画作呢
Just admiring the view.
看出来了
Yes.
品味不错 快回去工作 今晚有开幕式
Lovely. Now get back to work, we open tonight.
- 你不紧张吗？- 什么
- Doesn't it bother you? - What?
这幅画是伪造的
That the painting's a fake.
- 什么？- 假的
- What? - It's a fake.
它必须是 这是唯一的解释
It has to be. It's the only possible explanation.
你在这儿负责 对吗？
You are in charge, aren't you,
- 温斯莱斯小姐 - 你是谁
- Miss Wenceslas? - Who are you?
伍德布基知道它是伪造的
Alex Woodbridge knew that the painting was a fake,
所以有人派「泥人」来解决他 是你吗？
so somebody sent the Golem to take care of him. Was it you?
泥人？你在说什么？
Golem? What the hell are you talking about?
你在为别人工作吗？为他们伪造
Are you working for someone else? Did you fake it for them?
它不是伪造的
It's not a fake.
它是 我也不知道原因
It is a fake. I don't know why.
一定会有破绽 一定有
But there's something wrong with it, there has to be.
你知道什么？
What the hell are you on about?
- 我现在就可以把你开除 - 没问题
- You know I could have you sacked on the spot. - Not a problem.
- 没问题？- 对 我又不在这工作
- No? - No, I don't work here, you see.
只是走进来 给你个友好的建议
Just popped in to give you a bit of friendly advice.
你怎么进来的？
How did you get in?
- 拜托 - 我想知道
- Please! - I want to know.
在别人眼皮底下隐藏自己 就是伪装的艺术
The art of disguise is knowing how to hide in plain sight.
- 你是谁？- 夏洛克·福尔摩斯
- Who are you? - Sherlock Holmes.
我应该如雷贯耳吗？
Am I supposed to be impressed?
应该
You should be.
祝您有愉快的一天
Have a nice day.
他不会的 不会的
He wouldn't. He just wouldn't.
不
No.
- 世上无奇不有 - 小韦不是叛国贼
- Stranger things have happened. - Westie wasn't a traitor.
这样说太过分了
That's a horrible thing to say!
很抱歉 可是你要知道
I'm sorry.But you must understand…
他们这样想 对吧 他的老板？
That's what they think, isn't it, his bosses?
他是快结婚的年轻人 欠着债
He was young man, about to get married, he had debts.
人人都欠着债
Everyone's got debts,
小韦绝不可能为了还债 去出卖国家
and Westie wouldn't want to clear them by selling out his country.
你可以告诉我… 那晚究竟发生了什么吗？
Can you, er…? Can you tell me exactly what happened that night?
我们在家呆着
We were having a night in.
只是…看DVD
Just…watching a DVD.
平时他会睡着 可这次他没有
He normally falls asleep, you know, but he sat through this one.
他很沉默
He was quiet.
突然他就说要出去见个人
Out of the blue he said he just had to go and see someone.
你不知道是谁？
And you've no idea who?
嗨 丽兹 你还好吗？
Hi, Liz. You OK, love?
- 还好 - 他是谁？
- Yeah. - Who's this?
约翰·华生 你好
John Watson, hi.
这是我哥哥 乔伊
This is my brother, Joe.
约翰在调查小韦的事 乔伊
John's trying to find out what happened to Westie, Joe.
- 你是警局的人？- 算是吧
- You with the police? - Sort of, yeah.
你叫他们少管闲事 真他妈的岂有此理
Tell them to get off their arses, will you? It's bloody ridiculous.
我会尽力的
I'll do my best.
好吧
Well, er,
再次谢谢你的合作 我非常 非常遗憾
thanks very much for your help. Again, I'm very, very sorry.
他没有偷那些东西 华生先生
He didn't steal those things, Mr Watson.
我了解小韦 他是好男人
I knew Westie, he was a good man.
他是我的好男人
He was MY good man.
- 给点零钱吧 - 没有
- Spare change? - No.
给点零钱吧？
Any spare change?
艾利克斯·伍德布基对艺术毫无专长
Alex Woodbridge didn't know anything special about art.
- 而且？- 而且…
- And? - And…
就没了吗？爱好 个性？
Is that it? No habits, hobbies, personality?
别抢我话啊 他是业余天文学家
Give us a chance. He was an amateur astronomer.
叫住那辆出租
Hold that cab.
- 有零钱吗？- 还真有
- Spare change, sir? - Don't mind if I do.
（沃克斯豪尔拱门）
庆幸啊 我可没偷懒 上车
Fortunately, I haven't been idle. Come on.
真美 对吧
Beautiful, isn't it?
你不是懒得知道…
I thought you didn't care about…
不代表我不能欣赏它
Doesn't mean I can't appreciate it.
听着 伍德布基家的电话答录机里有条信息
Listen, Alex Woodbridge had a message on the answerphone at his flat.
- 一位凯安斯教授 - 这边
- A Professor Cairns. - This way.
好呀 城市里最美的地方
Nice. Nice part of town.
有什么要解释的吗？
Any time you want to explain?
流浪汉消息网
Homeless network.
- 真的太重要了 - 流浪汉消息网？
- Really is indispensable. - Homeless network?
我的眼线遍布整座城市
My eyes and ears, all over the city.
这…很聪明
Ah, that's…clever.
你给他们喂点食 然后？
So you scratch their backs, and…?
对 然后给自己消毒
Yes, then disinfect myself.
- 夏洛克 - 过来
- Sherlock! - Come on!
他在露宿吗？
What's he doing sleeping rough?
他长的很特别
Well, he has a very distinctive look.
必须藏起来避免闲话… 大多数闲话
He has to hide somewhere where tongues won't wag…much.
- 他妈的… - 什么？
- Oh sh… - What?
- 真希望我… - 没关系 别提了
- I wish I… - Don't mention it.
不 不
No! No! No! No!
再找到他又要花几周了
It'll take us weeks to find him again.
我可能知道他要去哪
Or I might have an idea where he might be going.
- 什么？- 我告诉过你
- What? - I told you,
有人给伍德布基留了言
Someone left Alex Woodbridge a message.
世上没几个凯安斯教授 来吧
There can't be that many Professor Cairns in the book. Come on.
木星 是太阳系的第五大行星 也是最大的
Jupiter, the fifth planet in our solar system, and the largest.
木星是一团巨大气体 地球只是它的十一分之一
Jupiter is a gas giant. Planet Earth would fit into it 11 times.
是的 我们都知道
Yes, we know that.
- 泰坦是最大的卫星… - 出来呀 海王星
- Titan is the largest moon… - Come on, Neptune.
很多已经熄灭多时
Many are actually long dead…
汤姆 是你吗？
Tom, is that you?
爆炸形成了超新星
…exploded into supernovas.
1864年被耶那维发现
Discovered by Urbain Le Verrier in 1846…
主要由氢气组成
…composed mainly of hydrogen.
其光芒需要很多年到达地球
Their light takes so long to reach us…
泥人
Golem!
很多早已熄灭 爆炸形成了…
…many are actually long dead, exploded into…
- 我看不到他 我从背后 - 我去
- I can't see him. I'll go round. - I'll go.
你这次为谁工作 杜斯拉？
Who are you working for this time, Dzundza?
星球的前身 坍缩物质团主要成分是…
A star begins as a collapsing ball of material composed mainly of…
泥人
Golem!
放开他
Let him go…
否则我杀了你
or I will kill you.
太阳系的第四行星
The fourth planet of the solar system,
名字取自罗马战神
named after the Roman god of war.
是一团巨大气体
…it is a gas giant…
需要很多年到达地球
…takes so long to reach us…
成了超新星
…into supernovas…
爆炸形成了超新星
…exploded into supernovas…
它是伪造的 肯定是
It's a fake. It has to be.
这画历经一切科学检测手段
That painting has been subjected to every test known to science.
那就是伪造的好
It's a very good fake, then.
你知道的 对吧 是你吧？
You know about this, don't you? This is you, isn't it?
探长 这是浪费我的时间
Inspector, my time is being wasted.
能不能请你和你朋友出去？
Would you mind showing yourself and your friends out?
这幅画是伪造的
The painting is a fake.
因此伍德布基和凯安斯被杀了
It's a fake, that's why Woodbridge and Cairns were killed.
得了 证明过程只是细节 画是伪造的
Oh, come on, proving it's just a detail. The painting is a fake.
我已经解决了 我想出来了
I've solved it, I've figured it out.
伪造的 这就是答案 他们被杀的原因
It's a fake, that's the answer, that's why they were killed.
好 我来证明
OK, I'll prove it.
给我时间 给我时间好吗？
Give me time. Will you give me time?
- 十 - 是个小孩
- Ten… - It's a kid.
天啊 是个小孩
Oh God, it's a kid.
- 他说什么？- 十
- What did he say? - "Ten."
- 九 - 他在倒数
- Nine… - It's a countdown.
他在给我时间
He's giving me time.
老天…是伪造的
Jesus… It's a fake,
可怎么证明 怎么证明？
but how can I prove it? How?! How?!
八
Eight.
这个小孩会死掉
This kid will die.
告诉我破绽在哪 告诉我
Tell me why the painting is a fake. Tell me!
- 七 - 不 闭嘴
- Seven… - No, shut up.
什么都别说 只能由我找到
Don't say anything. It only works if I figure it out.
一定有 就在我眼皮底下
It must be possible. It must be staring me in the face.
- 六 - 为什么？
- Six… - How?
- 伍德布基知道 为什么？- 五
- Woodbridge knew, but how?! - Five…
加速了 夏洛克
It's speeding up! Sherlock!
- 四 - 在天文馆 你也听到了
- Four… - Oh! In the Planetarium, you heard it too.
太棒了 太美妙了
Oh, that is brilliant, that is gorgeous!
- 三 - 什么太棒了？
- Three… - What's brilliant? What is?!
太美了 真厉害
This is beautiful. Love this!
天文学者 超新星
Astronomers, supernovas.
- 二 - 夏洛克
- Two… - Sherlock!
范布伦超新星
The Van Buren Supernova.
请问有人在吗？救救我
Please, is somebody there? Somebody help me.
换你了 去找到他的位置 救他
There you go. Go and find out where he is and pick him up.
所谓的范布伦超新星
Van Buren Supernova, so-called.
爆炸中的星 只在1858年出现过
Exploding star. Only appeared in the sky in 1858.
所以它怎么可能
So how could it have been…
在1640年代被画出来
painted in the 1640s?
（我的耐心有限 —麦克罗夫特·福尔摩斯）
夏洛克
Oh, Sherl…
这真有趣 波西米亚信笺
You know, it's interesting. Bohemian stationery,
以布拉格传说为名的杀手
an assassin named after a Prague legend,
还有你 温思莱斯小姐
and you, Miss Wenceslas.
这案子充满了捷克气息
This whole case has a distinctly Czech feeling about it.
这就是线索吗？
Is that where this leads?
这是什么罪 探长？
What are we looking at, Inspector?
刑事犯罪共谋 诈骗
Well, criminal conspiracy, fraud,
事后从犯 至少这些
accessory after the fact, at the very least.
谋杀老妇一名 还有一屋子人…
The murder of the old woman, all the people in the flat…
这些我不知道
I didn't know anything about that.
都不知道 求你了 相信我
All those things, please, believe me.
我只是参与分红
I just wanted my share.
三千万
The 30 million.
我在阿根廷发现一个小老头
I found a little old man in Argentina.
真是个天才
A genius, I mean, really.
画工 无懈可击
Brushwork, immaculate.
- 能糊弄过所有人 - 哼
- Could fool anyone. - Mmm.
几乎所有人
Well, nearly anyone.
可我也不知道怎么说服世人
But I didn't know how to go about convincing the world.
这幅画是真的
the picture was genuine.
这只是个想法
It was just an idea.
是他煽动我铸成大错
A spark which he blew into a flame.
谁？
Who?
我不知道
I don't know.
是真的
It's true!
花了很久 但最终我
It took a long time, but eventually I was…
和一些人接上了头
put in touch with people.
他的人
His people…
从没有过真正的联络
Well, there was never any real contact.
只有留言…
Just messages…
耳语
…whispers.
这些耳语有名字吗？
And did those whispers have a name?
莫里亚蒂
Moriarty.
- 韦斯特是在这里陈尸的？- 是的
- So this is where West was found? - Yeah.
- 会很久吗？- 也许
- Are you going to be long? - I might be.
- 你是警察吗？- 算是吧
- Are you the police, then? - Sort of.
- 我恨他们 - 警察？
- I hate 'em. - The police?
不 卧轨的
No, jumpers.
拦在火车前的人 自私鬼
People who chuck 'emselves in front of trains. Selfish bastards.
呃 这倒也是一说
Well, that's one way of looking at it.
我是真生气 他们倒轻巧
I mean it. It's all right for them.
几秒钟 草莓酱喷的满铁轨都是
It's over in a split second, strawberry jam all over the lines.
司机怎么办？
What about the drivers, eh?
他们就该认命吗？
They've got to live with it, haven't they?
对了 说到草莓酱 铁轨上没有血迹
Yeah, speaking of strawberry jam, there's no blood on the line.
- 已经清理了吗？- 不 没这么多
- Has it been cleaned off? - No, there wasn't that much.
你说他脑浆迸裂啊
You said his head was smashed in.
对 可是没很多血
It was, but there wasn't much blood.
好吧
OK.
那你在这儿看看吧
Well, I'll leave you to it, then.
- 走的时候叫一声 - 好的
- Just give us a shout when you're off. - Right.
好吧 韦斯特…在某处上车 真的吗？
Right, so, Andrew West…got on the train somewhere. Or did he?
尸体上却没有车票
There was no ticket on the body.
为什么陈尸这里？
How did he end up here?
- 道岔拐角 - 对
- The points. - Yes!
就知道你会明白的
I knew you'd get there eventually.
韦斯特没死在这儿 所以血迹这么少
West wasn't killed here, that's why there was so little blood.
- 你跟踪我多久了？- 从一开始
- How long have you been following me? - Since the start.
你不会以为我真会放弃这案子
You don't think I'd give up on a case like this.
就为了和我哥哥赌气吧？
just to spite my brother, do you?
走了 我们有个窃案要做
Come on, we've got a bit of burglary to do.
反导弹计划还没流出国
Missile defence plans haven't left the country,
否则麦克罗夫特的人会知道的
otherwise Mycroft's people would have heard about it.
不管人们怎么想 我们确实有特工
Despite what people think, we do still have a secret service.
明白 我见过他们
Yeah, I know, I've met them.
所以偷记忆棒的人没法卖掉它
Which means whoever stole the memory stick can't sell it.
或不知拿它怎么办
or doesn't know what to do with it.
我押后一种可能
My money's on the latter.
我们到了
We're here.
哪里？
Where?
夏洛克 如果有人在家怎么办？
Sherlock! What if there's someone in?
没有人
There isn't.
老天啊
Jesus…
我们在哪？
Where are we?
抱歉 我没说吗 乔伊·哈里森的家
Oh, sorry, didn't I say? Joe Harrison's flat.
乔伊
Joe…?
韦斯特未婚妻哥哥的家 他偷了记忆棒
Brother of West's fiancee. He stole the memory stick,
杀死了他的未来妹夫
killed his prospective brother-in-law.
他为什么要这样？
Then why did he do it?
那就问他吧
Let's ask him.
不要 不要
Don't! Don't.
我不是故意的…
I wasn't meant to…
露西会怎么说？老天
What's Lucy gonna say? Jesus.
你为什么杀他？
Why did you kill him?
这是意外 我发誓
It was an accident. I swear it was.
可偷走反导弹项目计划
But stealing the plans for the missile defence program.
并不是意外 对吧？
wasn't an accident, was it?
我参与毒品交易
I started dealing drugs.
自行车是个很好的掩护 对吧
I mean, the bike thing's a great cover, right?
也不知从什么时候开始
I don't know how it started.
我越陷越深
I just got out of my depth.
我欠人很多钱 危险的人
I owed people thousands. Serious people.
小韦快要订婚了 他开始谈他的工作
Then at Westie's engagement do, he starts talking about his job.
我是说 平时他也很小心
I mean, usually, he's so careful.
可那一晚 几杯以后 他开始无话不谈了
But that night, after a few pints, he really opened up.
他告诉了我这个计划
He told me about these missile plans.
绝密文件
Beyond top secret.
他给我看了记忆棒 在我面前晃着
He showed me the memory stick, he waved it in front of me.
这种东西不是常丢吗
You hear about these things getting lost,
落在垃圾堆里之类的
ending up on rubbish tips and whatnot.
但它就在我眼前 所以我想…
But there it was. And I thought…
我觉得可能值一大笔钱
Well, I thought it could be worth a fortune.
拿他东西太容易了 他烂醉如泥
It was pretty easy to get the thing off him, he was so plastered.
可我再见到他时
Next time I saw him,
他的表情告诉我 他知道了
I could tell by the look on his face that he knew.
你在这做什么？
What are you doing here?
- 你拿导弹计划去做什么？- 你胡说什么？
- What have you done with the plans? - What are you talking about?
后来呢？
What happened?
我准备叫救护车 可已经太迟了
I was going to call an ambulance, but it was too late.
我手足无措 就把他拖到了那儿
I just didn't have a clue what to do. So I dragged him in 'ere.
我坐在黑暗中 想着
I just sat in the dark, think it.
一个小聪明闯入你的大脑
When a neat little idea popped into your head.
把韦斯特远远搬离这里
Carrying Andrew West way away from here.
他的尸体会接着走很远
His body would have gone on for ages.
如果火车没有撞上变形道岔的话
if the train hadn't hit a stretch of track that curved.
或者尖道岔 正是
And points. Exactly.
记忆棒还在你这里吗？
Do you still have it, then the memory stick?
交给我吧 如果不介意的话
Fetch it for me, if you wouldn't mind.
转移注意力结束 游戏继续
Distraction over, the game continues.
也许游戏也结束了 投弹手再没来消息
Maybe that's over, too. We've heard nothing from the bomber.
五响 记得吧 约翰
Five pips, remember, John.
这是在倒数 现在只有四轮
It's a countdown.We've only had four.
错 错 错
No, no, no!
他当然不是男孩的爸爸
Of Course he's not the boy's father.
看他牛仔裤的折痕
Look at the turn-ups on his jeans!
- 我就知道这很危险 - 呃？
- I knew it was dangerous. - Hm?
叫你看肥皂剧
Getting you into crap telly.
和康妮·普林斯完全没法比
Not a patch on Connie Prince.
你把记忆棒给麦克罗夫特了吗？
Have you given Mycroft the memory stick yet?
给啦 他心花怒放
Yep. He was over the moon.
他又拿授勋来威胁我
Threatened me with a knighthood…again.
- 喂 我还在等呢 - 什么？
- You know, I'm still waiting. - Hm?
听你承认 懂一点点太阳系知识
For you to admit that a little knowledge of the solar system.
让你快速发现了假画的破绽
and you'd have cleared up the fake painting a lot quicker.
你又没赚到什么
It didn't do you any good, did it?
对 可我又不是世上唯一的咨询侦探
No, but I'm not the world's only consulting detective.
- 是啊 - 我不回来喝茶了
- True. - I won't be in for tea.
我去莎拉家了
I'm going to Sarah's.
冰箱里还有些意大利饭
There's still some of that risotto left in the fridge.
- 我们没牛奶了 - 我去买
- Milk, we need milk. - I'll get some.
- 真的？- 真的
- Really? - Really.
- 再买些豆子？- 嗯
- And some beans, then? - Mm.
（布鲁斯-帕廷顿计划已找到 请自取）
（游泳池 午夜）
给你带了一个见面礼
Bought you a little getting-to-know-you present.
是为了这个 对吧？
That's what it's all been for, isn't it?
你的这些谜题 逼我起舞
All your little puzzles, making me dance.
都为了不让我注意这个
All to distract me from this.
晚上好
Evening.
这倒很刺激 对吧 夏洛克？
This is a turn-up, isn't it, Sherlock?
约翰 到底怎么…？
John! What the hell…?
打赌你没料到这个
Bet you never saw this coming.
接下来 你想听我逼他说什么？
What…would you like me to make him say…next?
「叽里呱啦 叽里呱啦」
Gottle o' gear, gottle o' gear,
「舌头打结啦」 别说了
gottle o' gear. Stop it.
地方不错 游泳池
Nice touch, this. The pool,
小卡尔死的地方
where little Carl died.
我了结了他 也可以了结约翰·华生
I stopped him. I can stop John Watson, too.
- 了结他的心跳 - 你是谁？
- Stop his heart. - Who are you?
我给过你我的电话
I gave you my number.
还等着你打来呢
I thought you might call.
那是不是英国陆军勃朗宁手枪
Is that a British Army Browning.
型号L9A1 在你口袋里凸着
L9A1 in your pocket,
还是你见到我兴奋了？
or are you just pleased to see me?
都有
Both.
吉姆·莫里亚蒂 嗨
Jim Moriarty. Hi.
吉姆？
Jim?
医院那个吉姆？
Jim from the hospital?
哦 我真的演得那么像啊
Oh, did I really make such a fleeting impression?
可是我想 这就是重点
But then, I suppose, that was rather the point.
别傻了 别人拿着来福枪呢
Don't be silly. Someone else is holding the rifle.
我可不想脏了我的手
I don't like getting my hands dirty.
我给过你暗示 夏洛克 一点点提示
I've given you a glimpse, Sherlock, just a teensy glimpse.
关于我在那广大的世界做了什么
of what I've got going on out there in the big bad world.
我是个专家 你看
I'm a specialist, you see.
和你一样
Like you.
亲爱的吉姆
Dear Jim…
请问能帮我
…please will you fix it for me.
摆脱情人那讨厌的姐妹吗？
to get rid of my lover's nasty sister?
亲爱的吉姆 可以让我跑路去南美吗？
Dear Jim, please will you fix it for me to disappear to South America?
就是这样
Just so.
「咨询罪犯」
Consulting criminal.
- 厉害 - 对吧
- Brilliant. - Isn't it?
没人找上过我
No-one ever gets to me.
将来也不会找到
And no-one ever will.
我找到了
I did.
你很接近了 现在你妨碍我了
You've come the closest. Now you're in my way.
- 谢谢 - 这不是称赞
- Thank you. - Didn't mean it as a compliment.
- 就是 - 好吧 算是
- Yes, you did. - Yeah, OK, I did.
可是调戏时间该结束了 夏洛克
But the flirting's over, Sherlock.
爸爸受够了
Daddy's had enough now.
我展示了我的能力
I've shown you what I can do.
我解脱了那么多人 那么多小麻烦
I cut loose all those people, all those little problems,
放弃了三千万 只求你过来和我玩
even 30 million quid, just to get you to come out and play.
把它看成一个友爱的警告吧 亲爱的
So take this as a friendly warning… my dear.
退后
Back off.
尽管我非常享受
Although I have loved this,
我们间的小游戏
this little game of ours.
扮演IT员工吉姆 扮演同性恋
Playing Jim from IT. Playing gay.
你喜欢我内裤的小把戏吗？
Did you like the little touch with the underwear?
- 有人为此死了 - 人都会死
- People have died. - That's what people do!
- 我会制止你 - 不 你不会
- I will stop you. - No, you won't.
你还好吧？
Are you all right?
你可以说话 小约翰
You can talk, Johnny boy.
说啊
Go ahead.
- 拿去 - 嗯？哦…
- Take it. - Mm? Oh…
这个？导弹计划
…that? The missile plans.
真无聊
Boring!
我随便都可以拿到
I could have got them anywhere.
夏洛克 快跑
Sherlock, run!
好呀
Good!
很好
Very good.
如果你的阻击手开枪 莫里亚蒂先生 我们都没命
If your sniper pulls that trigger, Mr Moriarty, then we both go up.
好贴心哎 明白你为什么喜欢他在身边了
Isn't he sweet? I can see why you like having him around.
不过 人总是对自己的宠物太心软
But then, people do get so sentimental about their pets.
它们忠诚得感人
They're so touchingly loyal.
可是 唉
But oops!
你可露出破绽了 华生医生
You've rather shown your hand there, Dr Watson.
逮到你了
Gotcha.
维斯特伍德西服 你知道不放过我
Westwood. Do you know what happens.
你会有什么下场吗 夏洛克？
if you don't leave me alone, Sherlock? To you?
让我猜猜 被杀掉
Oh, let me guess. I get killed.
杀你？
Kill you?
别没创意了 当然有一天我会杀掉你
No, don't be obvious. I mean, I'm going to kill you anyway, some day.
我可不想这么快
I don't want to rush it, though.
我要留着 来些特别节目
I'm saving it up for something special.
不不 要是你继续多管闲事 我让你生不如死
No, no, no, no, no. If you don't stop prying, I'll burn you.
让你像掏心一般痛不欲生
I'll burn the heart out of you.
有个可靠的人告诉我 我根本没有心
I have been reliably informed that I don't have one.
可我们都知道这不太正确
But we both know that's not quite true.
好吧 我要走了
Well, I'd better be off.
总算能有次像样的谈话了
Well, so nice to have had a proper chat.
如果我现在开枪射你呢？
What if I was to shoot you now?
就现在？
Right now?
那你可以好好珍藏我惊讶的表情
Then you could cherish the look of surprise on my face.
因为我会惊讶的 夏洛克
Cos I'd be surprised, Sherlock.
真的会
Really, I would.
然后会有一点点…失望
And just a teensy bit…disappointed.
而且你也不会珍藏太久的
And of course, you wouldn't be able to cherish it for very long.
再见 夏洛克·福尔摩斯
Ciao, Sherlock Holmes.
回头…再抓你
Catch you…later.
想得美
No, you won't!
还好吗？你还好吗？
All right? Are you all right?
对 我没事 我没事 夏洛克
Yeah, I'm fine. I'm fine. Sherlock…
夏洛克
Sherlock!
上帝啊
Oh, Christ.
- 你还好吧？- 我？我没事 没事
- Are you OK? - Me? Yeah, fine. I'm fine. Fine.
刚才…刚才你…你做的事…
That, er…thing that you… that you did,
你准备为我做的…呃…挺好的
that, um…you offered to do… that was, um…good.
- 幸好没人看到 - 什么？
- I'm glad no-one saw that. - Mm?
你在黑暗的泳池边扒我衣服
You ripping my clothes off in a darkened swimming pool.
大家会说闲话的
People might talk.
他们就没别的本事
They do little else.
抱歉 男孩们 我老是那么变化无常
Sorry, boys. I'm so changeable!
这是我的缺点 可老实说
It is a weakness with me, but to be fair to myself,
是我的唯一缺点
it is my only weakness.
不能允许你们继续了
You can't be allowed to continue.
不许继续了
You just can't.
我会尽量说服你
I would try to convince you,
可我想说的 你大概都已经想到了
but everything I have to say has already crossed your mind.
也许我的答案你也心知肚明
Probably my answer has crossed yours.